acm.org 2000-06-08

# Draft ACM privacy policy

  |  **DRAFT ACM Privacy Policy**

Dear ACM Member:

As a major organization in the information technology field, it is essential that ACM take a leadership position in crafting a Privacy Policy. In fact, one of the imperatives of [ACM's Code of Ethics](http://www.acm.org/constitution/code.html#sect1) (1.7), deals with respecting the privacy of others.

Since the purpose of this policy should be to protect the rights and the confidentiality of its members (see [ACM Code of Ethics](http://www.acm.org/constitution/code.html#sect1), 1.8), it follows that drafting such a policy should be a participatory project, a collaborative effort that attempts to define not only the reasons for establishing specific policies but helps define some of the much talked about and cited cyber intrusions, such as "unsolicited email"  and the very nature of contact itself.

At the same time members will be commenting on this Draft of ACM's overall Privacy Policy, the ACM Committee On Privacy Policy, will be revising this draft based on member comment. These revisions will be posted on the Web at <http://www.acm.org/serving/> periodically for you to understand how member comment has re-shaped the original draft.

In soliciting member comments on the attached document we're hoping that members who are deeply interested in privacy issues come forward and identify themselves so that new grass-roots efforts can be created.

Once a final draft of the Privacy Policy is established, ACM will undertake a thorough review of its practices and make the necessary changes to comply with the new policy.

Please send your comments on the draft ACM Privacy Policy to: [privacy@acm.org](mailto:privacy@acm.org). Please also see the [archive](http://www.acm.org/serving/acm-privacy1.html) of comments received.

Sincerely, 

Lorrie Cranor  
ACM Privacy Committee 

DRAFT ACM Privacy Policy 24 September 1998

[This draft Privacy Policy is posted for feedback purposes only. It does not represent current ACM policy. Comments appear in square brackets. Send comments to [privacy@acm.org](mailto:privacy@acm.org)]

The Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) is committed to protecting the privacy of its members and customers. This policy applies to the Association as well as to its special interest groups, chapters, and other sub-units. 

ACM maintains member databases that contain mailing, billing, and member profile information, as well as a record of each member's product and service purchases. ACM also maintains databases of non-member purchases and of registrations for conferences and other ACM activities. The information in these databases is used by authorized ACM staff members to process orders; mail invoices, purchases, renewal notices, and announcements; respond to member inquiries; and help us improve our offerings. Member records are maintained as long as an individual is an ACM member and for two years following a membership lapse. Purchase and registration databases may be retained for up to two years. All personally identifiable information contained in ACM membership, purchase, and registration databases is treated with strict confidentiality and will be used only for the purposes stated in this policy, except where required by law. These records will not be "enhanced" or overlaid with data from other sources. In addition, specific practices with respect to email addresses, postal addresses, information provided for the ACM Membership Directory, and information collected through the ACM Web site and ACM Web accounts are described below. [Note, ACM currently does not have a record retention policy. However, as records more than two years old are rarely if ever used, we recommend that ACM adopt the more privacy-friendly practice of purging database entries after two years, retaining only aggregate or anonymized information. We need to determine whether there are any legal problems with doing that. We also need to add a statement about how ACM will respond to subpeonas]

**ACM members may access the information contained in their membership records and correct and update their member profile and mailing information online at<http://www.acm.org/membership/dir/profile.html> or by contacting ACM's Member Services Department by phone: +1-212-626-0500, 1-800-342-6626, fax: +1-212-944-1318, or email: acmhelp@acm.org.**

### Email

ACM does not sell or rent email addresses. ACM uses email addresses to send the following: 

  1. "Must Have" messages that help to service ACM members including answers to member questions; acknowledgments of the receipt of membership applications and other orders; and membership renewal notices. 
  2. Occasional "Member Update" announcements about ACM services that we believe to be of some importance to members. These announcements are short straightforward messages that contain pointers to online resources where members can explore the information more fully.
  3. Email messaging that is part of a program for which the member has registered (e.g. an ACM Digital Library early alert email system). 
  4. Mailing lists disseminating information to targeted ACM groups (e.g. special interest group listservs, chapter listservs). 

All ACM email lists -- including the Member Update list -- and ACM programs that send automatic email messages have easy to follow "unsubscribe" instructions. 

### Postal Mail

ACM provides five mailing list options to its members: 

  1. Receive ACM invoices and products ordered only. 
  2. Receive ACM invoices and products ordered, and announcements from ACM and its sub-units; do not receive ACM Member Value Plus announcements. 
  3. Receive ACM invoices, products, and announcements from ACM and its sub-units including ACM Member Value Plus announcements. (This is the default option.) 
  4. In addition to ACM mailings, receive announcements from sister societies. 
  5. In addition to ACM mailings, receive mailings from companies and other organizations including announcements and advertisements for books, magazines, journals, computer software and hardware, courses, and financial programs. 

Members may select one of the above options by contacting ACM's Member Services Department or updating their member profile online. [These options will also be printed on future membership forms.]

The names and mailing addresses of members who have selected options 4 or 5 may be rented to outside organizations to send mailing packages that have been carefully screened by authorized ACM staff for their suitability. ACM member names and mailing addresses are never sold. [Currently all members have option 4 by default, unless they opt out. ACM mailing list sales bring in about $290,000 per year, or about $3.50 per member each year. Therefore, switching to the opt-in policy as recommended here, might require a small dues increase to make up for the lost mailing list revenue. We recommend that members continue to receive ACM announcements including MVP announcements by default because we assume that if you join ACM, you have an interest in receiving information about the association's services and membership benefits. Also, to avoid confusion we recommend that future MVP mailings be clearly identified with the ACM MVP logo.]

The names and mailing addresses contained in ACM product and registration databases may be used for mailing invoices, products ordered, and ACM announcements only. Individuals can ask not to receive ACM announcements at the time they register or place an order. [Again, we recommend that people who order ACM products or register for ACM events receive ACM announcements by default.]

### Membership Directory

The ACM Membership Directory was created to identify the members of ACM to one another, and promote the sharing of ideas and dissemination of information among members. This Directory is accessible only to ACM members and ACM Special Interest Group (SIG) members. Members can search only the Directory records for the groups to which they belong. 

By default, each member's name, city, state or province, and country are included in the Directory. No other information about an ACM member (including street address) will be included in the Directory unless the member decides to add information. The information that can be included in a member's Directory listing is taken from the member's profile data, and members can include as much or as little information as they wish.  Members can remove their information from the Membership Directory or add information by updating their [online profiles](http://www.acm.org/membership/dir/profile.html). ACM encourages members to include their email addresses and other information in the Directory as a way of facilitating quality networking and information sharing. 

The Directory may not be used for commercial purposes or to generate lists for bulk mailings. In order to prevent the harvesting of Directory information, searches will return a limited number of names that match the search criteria. To see any additional information that a member has chosen to include in the Directory, the searcher must select a particular member name. 

### ACM Web Site

This policy applies to the "acm.org" Web site maintained by ACM. ACM sub-units and individual ACM members are encouraged to adopt similar policies for their Web sites. 

Other than in the restricted-access portions of our site that require an ACM Web Account, ACM does not log the identity of visitors. However, we may keep access logs, for example containing a visitor's IP address and search queries. We may analyze log files periodically to help maintain and improve our Web site, and enforce our online service polices. Cookies are used to maintain user information only in the restricted-access portions of our site. Raw (not aggregated or anonymized) log files are treated with strict confidentiality and retained for no longer than two years. 

On some pages of our site we allow individuals to submit information for the purposes of joining ACM; renewing or updating their membership; ordering products and services; or registering for participation in a conference, contest, or other activity. Information collected on these pages will be placed in the appropriate ACM database and used according to the ACM Privacy Policy. 

### ACM Web Accounts

Some portions of the ACM Web site, including the ACM Digital Library, require an ACM Web account. To create an account, ACM members must provide their name, ACM member number, and email address. They are assigned a "username" (which they may change) and asked to create a password and provide the day and month of their birth (for account verification purposes). 

Non-members must setup an ACM Web account in order to use the "Search" facility in the ACM Digital Library. Non-members are asked for their name, email address, and postal address when they create their account. By default, ACM may send information about ACM products and services to non-member ACM Web account holders via email. Non-members may request that they not receive such information when they create their account. 

Information collected about ACM Web account usage -- including logs of Web pages visited, searches performed, and Digital Library content downloaded -- will be stored in an anonymized form and used to improve the ACM Digital Library and other ACM Web offerings. [This information is currently not anonymized, but as long as some demographic information is tied to each anonymized user name, it does not appear that it is necessary to identify users by name in these logs, except perhaps to track down abuse -- for example copyright violations or abuse of Member Directory information. This issue should be discussed further.] Other information provided in the process of creating or using a Web account will be placed in the appropriate ACM database and used according to the ACM Privacy Policy. 

Please send your comments on the draft ACM Privacy Policy to: [privacy@acm.org](mailto:privacy@acm.org).  
Comments are archived and may be viewed at <http://www.acm.org/archives/privacy.html>. 

The previous draft of this policy is available at <http://www.acm.org/serving/acm-privacy1.html>
